Christopher L. Cox

epistibrain.github.io

Contact
Information

(309) 472-4870

clcox@tarleton.edu

2018-Present

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research aims to broadly understand no-slip billiards, a mechanical model in which angular and linear momentum may be conservatively exchanged at collisions. Using analytic and computational techniques, I am working to fill in a narrative beginning with a physically motivated geometric model, continuing with the dynamics of the consequent billiards, and then opening the door to incorporating rotational models into thermodynamics, statistical mechanics, and non-holonomic systems.

EMPLOYMENT

Tarleton State University

Assistant Professor of Mathematics

University of Delaware

Visiting Assistant Professor of Mathematics 2017-2018

Washington University in St. Louis

Postdoctoral Teaching Fellow 2016-2017

Illinois Central College

Professor of Mathematics 1998-2011

EDUCATION

Washington University in St. Louis

Ph.D. in Mathematics 2016

• Dissertation: No-slip Billiards, Advisor: Renato Feres

Northwestern University M.S. in Mathematics

M.S. in Mathematics

Williams College B.A. in Mathematics

B.A. Cum Laude, with honors in Mathematics 1992

PUBLICATIONS

- T. Chumley, S. Cook, C. Cox, R. Feres, *Rolling and no-slip bouncing in cylinders*, Journal of Geometric Dynamics, to appear, (arxiv:1808.08448).
- C. Boone, C. Cox, E. Smith, Specular and no-slip billiards with cusps, Proceedings of the ICTCM, to appear.
- C. Cox, R. Feres, H.-K. Zhang, Stability of periodic orbits of no-slip billiards, Nonlinearity, 31 (10), 2018, 4433-4471.
- C. Cox, R. Feres *No-slip billiards in dimension two*, Dynamical Systems, Ergodic Theory, and Probability: in Memory of Kolya Chernov, Contemporary Mathematics, vol. 698, Amer. Math. Soc., Providence, RI, 2017, 91-110.
- M. Correia, C. Cox, H.-K. Zhang, *Ergodicity in umbrella billiards*, New Horizons in Mathematical Physics, 1 (2), 2017, 56-67.

C. Cox, R. Feres, Differential geometry of rigid bodies collisions and non-standard billiards, Discrete and Continuous Dynamical Systems A 36 (11), 2016, 6065-6099.

C. Cox, Flow-dependent networks: Existence and behavior at Steiner points, Networks 31 (1998), no. 3, 149-156.

TEACHING Tarleton State University

Assistant Professor 2018-Present

• Taught undergraduate and graduate courses, from College Algebra to graduate level Math Modeling.

- Math Club faculty sponsor Fall 2018 through Fall 2019.
- Putnam Lunch faculty sponsor Fall 2019.
- Ran a summer REU program (with Scott Cook) for four undergraduates, supported by two internal and one external grant.
- Along with other Tarleton faculty, took over fifty students to undergraduate research conference over three semester. The majority were involved in talks or poster sessions.
- Worked with a master's student researching billiards of varying mass distribution, supported by an internal grant.
- Hosted three guests for department talks on undergraduate math research, sports analytics, and using Monte Carlo methods for decryption.

University of Delaware

Visiting Assistant Professor

2017-2018

- Taught Calculus, Linear Algebra, and Differential Equations
- Served as coordinator for Multivariable Calculus
- Served as a poster session judge at the graduate research fair
- Hosted one guest for a department colloquium

Washington University

Postdoctoral Fellow

2016-2017

• Teaching duties included Calculus, Linear Algebra, and Combinatorics

Teaching Assistant

2011-2015

- Taught Calculus in the Freshman Summer Academic Program, Foundations of Calculus
- Teaching Assistant for Differential Equations
- $\bullet\,$ Tutor at the Calculus Help Room
- Grader for graduate level Differential Geometry, Algebraic Topology, Point Set Topology, and Fourier Analysis

Illinois Central College

Professor of Mathematics

1998-2011

- Taught Calculus I, II, and III, Differential Equations, Discrete Math, Finite Math, Statistics, College and Intermediate Algebra, Calculus for Business and Social Science.
- Experience with distance learning, including teaching DL classes to rural high schools allowing students to complete the Calculus sequence.
- Taught online College Algebra and Business Calculus open sections for nine years,

- as well as designated dual-credit sessions for high school students.
- Extensive committee work, including hiring, syllabus and compliance, textbook, college accreditation, faculty forum, ICC Educational Foundation campaign, and community outreach committees.
- Extracurricular activities included Student Math League (coach), WYSE and Illinois Council of Teachers of Mathematics high school competitions.
- Supervised honors projects for math majors and served as director of the Honors Program.

Selected Talks

Research Talks



	Math Circles	and Tarks for General Audiences	
	 Opportunities for Students in Numerical Simulation of Billiards, International Conference on Technology in College Mathematics. (March 2019) An Introduction to No-slip Billiards, Tarleton University Math Club, Stephenville, Texas. (March 2018) 		
	□ Partitions of the plane, Washington University Math Circle, St. Louis. (September		
	2016) ☐ The mathematics of billiards, Washington University Math Circle, St. Louis. (March		
	2016) □ An introduction to billiard dynamics, ICTM Math Contest, Illinois Central College,		
	East Peoria, IL. (February 2016) Some dynamics of rough collisions, Szego Seminar, Washington University, St. Louis. (March 2015)		
	(March 2015) ☐ The lazy caterer and graceful configurations, ICTM Math Contest, Illinois Central College, East Peoria, IL. (February 2015)		
	☐ Cutting pancakes, cake and cheese, Washington University Math Circle, St. Louis. (October 2014)		
	☐ A generalized Hamilton-Jacobi problem, Szego Seminar, Washington University, St. Louis. (February 2014)		
	☐ Length minimizing partitions of the sphere, Graduate Student Seminar, Washington University, St. Louis. (July 2012)		
	☐ Steiner networks, Washington University Math Circle, St. Louis. (February 2012)		
Fellowships,	November 2019	ICERM Workshop on Illustrating Dynamics and Probability.	
GRANTS, AND SUPPORTED RESEARCH	August 2018	Simons Early Career Travel Grant, International Congress of Mathematicians, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.	
	2015-2017	Stochastic Thermodynamics and Random Billiards. Structured Quartet Research Ensemble, American Institute of Math, San Jose, CA. Tim Chumley (organizer), Hongkun Zhang, Renato Feres, Scott Cook, and Matt Wallace.	
	2015-2016	Dissertation Fellowship. Washington University in St. Louis.	
	May 2015	Houston Summer School on Dynamical Systems. University of Houston, Houston, TX.	
	2013, 2014	Summer Research Assistant. for Xiang Tang, supported by the National Science Foundation.	
	2011-2012	University Fellowship. Washington University in St. Louis.	
	2001	ICC Educational Foundation Grant. Awarded to support the development of an online College Algebra course.	
	1991, 1992	SMALL REU Summer Undergraduate Research Program. Advisors: Frank Morgan and Tom Garrity. Williams College, Williamstown, MA.	
Relevant Skills	Programming:	Python, Sage, Mathematica, especially billiard modeling.	
		WeBWork, WebAssign, and MyMathLab.	
	LMS:	Blackboard, Sakai, and Canvas.	